Guide to the Eugene Field Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Eugene Field collection
1880-1894
YCAL MSS 508
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
Contains autograph manuscript drafts of poems by Eugene Field and autograph letters signed from Field to various individuals.
Field, Eugene, 1850-1895
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. Provenance is listed at folder level when known.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Eugene Field, 1850-1895
Eugene Field, Chicago poet and journalist.
Scope and Contents
Contains autograph manuscript drafts of poems by Eugene Field and autograph letters signed from Field to various individuals.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1880-1898. II. Writings, 1888-1892.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century; Poets, American -- 19th century; Poets -- United States -- 19th century; Field, Eugene, 1850-1895
- Correspondence, 1880-1898, undated; Series I; 14
  - To Field from various, 1880-1898
    Scope and Contents
    Eight folders of letters to Eugene Field from various people
    Custodial History
    Gift of Carol J. Neufeld and Morris A. Neufeld, November 1950
    - A-B (Box 1)
      Irving Bacheller, Manin A Baker, Page M. Baker, John F. Ballantyne, Phineas Taylor Barnum, Wilson Barrett, Belford Clarke & Co., J. E. Blaine, Edward William Bok, Jessie W. Bolté, E. Brainard, G. E. Bridgman, J. S. C. Brown, Francis Fisher Browne, Edward Hubert Butler
    - C-D (Box 1)
      George W. Cable, Louise S. Cable, J. Cleveland Cady, B. B. Cahoon, W. T. Carleton, Julia A. Carney, Clark Ezra Carr, Mary H. Catherwood, Francis James Child, George W. Childs, Albert Clarke, Cecil Clay
    - E-G (Box 1)
    - H-L (Box 1)
    - M-R (Box 1)
    - S-T (Box 1)
    - U-Z (Box 1)
    - First names only and unidentified (Box 1)
  - From Field to Colonel Thomas Wentworth Higginson, autograph letter signed, undated (Box 1)
    Gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911
  - From Field to Miss Hutchinson, 2 autograph letters signed, 1893 November 23, 1984 May 17 (Box 1)
  - From Field to Benjamin H. Ticknor, 3 autograph letters signed, 1887 April-August (Box 1)
    Removed from his Second Book of Tales, New York, 1896; his Little Book of Profitable Tales, Chicago, 1889; his Cultural Garden, Boston 1887
    Gift of Owen Aldis, 1911
  - From Field to Julia Sutherland Comstock, 2 autograph letters signed, 1873 June 12, November 24 (Box 1)
    The first letter was written before Field's marriage to Miss Comstock
    Gift of Philip D. Sang, 1955
  - From Field to "My Dear Taylor," autograph letter signed, 1894 May 12 (Box 1)
    Gift of R. A. Kaufman, 1956
  - From Field to "Dear Sir", 1890 February 8 (Box 1)
    Purchased from James Thin, 1956
- Writings, 1888-1892, undated; Series II; 5
  - "The Bereaved Bridegroom," first chapter, original manuscript with two illustrations, undated (Box 1)
    Gift of Philip Neufeld, date unknown
  - "Little-Oh-Dear," manuscript copy, signed, of last verse of this poem, with colored illustration at head of card, 1894 June 25 (Box 1)
    General note
    Removed from copy of his Love-Songs of Childhood, New York, 1894
  - Six-line quotation commencing "Of waistcoats there are diverse kinds," in his handwriting, signed, 1882 May (Box 1)
    Removed from his copy of Little Book of Western Verse, Chicago, 1889
  - "Sharps and Flats," one page manuscript numbered "1", undated (Box 1)
  - "To E[dmund]. C[larence]. S[tedman]," original manuscript, signed, 1888 May 17 (Box 1)
    A letter in the form of a twenty-line poem, with rubricated initials at the beginning of the stanzas
    Gift of Mrs. Paul Moore,1956